He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc.
Chapter 48 verses 4-5
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits,
Angels, demons and saints in our
time many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate every day life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
creation. The union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers, scorpion stompers.
You are listening to Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host, the very Reverend Doctor Stephen D'Young,
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana,
where it is a 1,000 degrees and 200 percent humidity.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Daymakin
and the cool, clear, lovely.
You may as Pennsylvania and we're back live. So if you are listening to us live
You can call us at 855-237-2346 and you can talk to us and we're gonna get to your calls in the second half of the show
It's great to be live again after the last two pre-recorded episodes in July
Although next time we're gonna have to do another pre-record as I will be away. Oh
Well tonight though. We're eating the country. I know I know I'm
I'm headed across an ocean
Yeah, yeah.
Tonight we're going to continue our series on eschatology.
We're talking about what is commonly referred to as the second coming of Christ.
But is that the right way to refer to it?
And why is the Messiah coming twice anyway?
After the Ascension, are we just sort of waiting around for him, trying to hang on until he
comes back?
Or is there something happening?
So Father, are we just in pause mode?
Jesus is doing something else.
for a while. No. That was a good pause though. Yeah. Kind of been a little bit more
pregnant pause, but it was it was a pause. I would I would I would just like to thank
all the boomers listening for not sorting your recyclables, causing much of this
part of the country to be on fire currently.
Oh wow.
Is that what does it?
That's what I'm told.
So I've heard.
More summer recorded history.
You guys couldn't ride your bike store.
Thanks, bunches.
We've just lost it on our super...
Anyways.
You know who you are.
Those who just tuned out.
Yes.
Oh, there's a couple groups.
Right.
The boobers who are offended took me literally.
There's the other people who are
bad that I made a joke about climate change rhetoric. There's another group that
thinks I was acknowledging climate change. They're also tuning out. So I really find
toon these things to alienate as many people as possible with each word.
Well, you know, we we can stand to lose a few listeners. Yeah, even after postigate,
Right.
We still have a few we could spare.
Oh, that was a real calling.
Right.
It's true. Yeah, I think we lost a lot of people after you said that pasta's wet bread. They were like
deeply offended. Yes. Yes.
But I call them like I see them. You're right. You gotta just
somebody had to say it. We were all thinking
Right, so
Yes
You know, there's the whole debate about whether the Earth is going to be destroyed this time with fire and while I have a certain amount of anecdotal evidence at the moment to agree with that.
We're actually talking about what's generally termed Christ second coming tonight.
I mean, some say it will be destroyed in ice.
which would survive twice as nice.
I'm blanking on the actual.
wording of that poem. Yeah, ice is too close to water, man.
Like zan could change both into water and into ice. Oh, wow, that's just like jane I could do any
animal. Yeah. Right. So like that's too close to the flood. Now we're stepping in the
whole wonder twins theme that Steve Christopher and Christian Gonzalez had going on in pop culture
coffee hour. We go to deep cuts, or at least I could go into deep cuts on the wonder twins.
Yeah.
that I think no one wants that.
But they are better than, you know, they replaced
another group of sidekicks.
Are you aware of this?
That's super friends.
Oh boy.
I mean, I remember watching that show a lot
when I was quite young.
I mean, I had a great fondness for Hannah Barbira cartoons
in those days.
I mean, it was just a ridiculous show.
There's a segment of our list or base
that just loves this.
kind of stuff at the beginning of the show.
Right.
Zan and Jaina were the hip-cool Vulcan replacements.
We're the purple outfit for Marvin, Wendy, and Wonder Dog.
Wow.
I vaguely remember that.
I remember Wonder Dog.
Man, I'm going to have to go look that up after the show.
And if you want to go really deep cut,
there are only reasons I've said this over the air
to prove that
to everyone. Once and for all, you do not want to mess with me in pop culture trivia.
Wendy of Marvin Wendy and Wonder Dog was actually Wendy Prince and was the niece of the military
nurse whose identity Wonder Woman took over to be her secret identity after the original Diana
and a Prince Dung. Nice.
Been World War II.
So, no one will ever come at me in Pub trivia now.
But anyway, yes, Christ returned.
Is what we're talking about tonight.
If someone does come at you on Pub trivia,
we know that it will be a herald of the end of days.
Yeah, if two nerds.
that dance coming to contact with each other.
I think it would open up some kind of rift.
Yeah.
We got, we just got a,
we just got a comment on Facebook saying,
we can do better than Robert Frost on this podcast.
How dare you, sir.
How dare you?
I just did better than Robert Frost.
Oh, come on.
I gave you,
I mean, there's better in those history of Marvin,
Wendy and what are going on?
That is pretty wonderful, but, you know,
Something there is that doesn't love anyway
Moving on
I mean I'm not a huge. It's okay. It's okay. You don't have to be I could go
But you know, it wouldn't this be a nice time in Louisiana to stop by woods in a snowy evening just throwing that out there
It's not possible. Yeah, so
Yeah, so it just makes you feel worse
Yeah, I was I was so desperate.
on Sunday that I said we were celebrating Holy Theophany.
Oh wow.
Instead of transfiguration.
That's how desperately I wanted it to be January.
Please.
Yes.
We're only like what, 85 on January 6th?
Yeah, yeah.
Man.
Toasty 78 outside.
The AC works.
Can handle that.
So yes, the return of Christ.
which we're actually going to start.
talking about, I mean, I know we've now just wasted a bunch of your time with that whole intro, but
we're actually going to start talking about the topic here in the first half. So there's that.
So we're balancing that out a little bit. Yeah, there's that.
And obviously this is sort of a critically important part of our eschatology series.
and we've obviously also already alluded to it, we alluded it.
alluded to it back in the Antichrist episode,
what we talked about.
The Antichrist being destroyed by the breath of his mouth
at Christ appearing.
We talked about it obliquely in the millennium episode.
Obviously last judgment Christ is the judge, right.
But now we're sort of gonna go head on to this.
and
There are a number of issues surrounding this.
They've got to give people the lay of the land
of why this is something that needs to be addressed.
Because probably a lot of our listenership
since the majority numerically of our listenership
is in the United States.
The return of Jesus Christ is something
that has probably been of an outsized importance
in their religious life.
Yeah.
And I was just saying in our pre-show that I have a digital copy of the Lake Quake Planet Earth
by Hal Lindsey, you know, and I threatened to read parts of it on air and you weirdly
says something about copyright.
But yeah, I mean, I don't believe in it, but right now I can be victimized by it.
Yeah, but I mean, yeah, like the idea that Jesus is coming back soon, I mean like literally
there's here in America, a foreign listeners, there are billboards, you can be just driving
down the road.
And you-
you'll see a billboard or some random little sign or even just a bumper sticker or step
up to somebody's house and see a sign that says, Jesus is coming back soon.
You know, or my favorite, prepare to meet thy God, you know, kind of vaguely threat.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, this is, it's not everywhere present, but I mean, it's definitely a thing.
It's definitely a part of American culture, this sort of military and idea.
Yeah, and...
There are a not insignificant number of sort of
parachurched ministries out there who present the gospel in terms of Christ's return.
They present the gospel as Christ is returning soon.
You need to get right with God so you don't end up getting sent to hell.
Yeah. The last judgment. Yeah.
Right. That's explicitly how they present the gospel.
Ending of every episode of Jack Van A. P. Presents, right.
both in his early Mastashio days and his later
clean shaven days.
Yeah, so yeah, for a lot of people taking on an
outsized sort of importance.
But we're going to be coming at it as is our want.
More from the perspective of the way it's treated in terms of
discussions of ancient Christianity and
and the scriptures and the Bible,
where it's treated as, first of all,
is sort of this weird Christian novo,
in the sense that it's presumed
that there's not an inkling of this anywhere in the Hebrew Bible,
or even the Christian Old Testament,
that the idea that Christ left somewhere in the ascension,
and is going to come back with some kind of cope basically by his disciples
to explain why Christ didn't start the Messianic age immediately.
Oh, he's coming back.
And then he's going to do all that other stuff.
Right?
Right.
And because in large part, because it's assumed to be this cope,
then it's assumed that well they
expected him to come back during their own lifetimes. Not in the sense that they thought he could
return at any time, but like they concretely believed, no, he's going to come back within like 40
years or something. Yeah. And then, you know, there's this whole idea then, well, once you assume
that well okay so then that means that
All these ideas like just the churches and organization or institution
Sacraments all these things those must all be later
After everybody got disappointed. Yeah, because why would you do all that stuff if Jesus is gonna come back like any second?
Right and therefore
Since this was just this code
It was until that blew up that they said oh well. I guess we need to lay down roots and build this
Build this institution
And then what you would presume if any of that were true would be that sort of the expectation
of Christ's return would go away, which if you've studied any church history, you know
is not the case.
In fact there have been several significant periods of this kind of fervor that's come
around and the came around and
And in American evangelicalism in the latter half of the 20th century has happened a whole
bunch of times in the past.
Yeah, I mean, just even just the 19th century in America, like my personal favorite, the
Millerites who came out here to Pennsylvania and, you know, gathered in the wilderness,
waiting, I think it was, it was 1842, like October 19th, 1842.
I'm just throwing that off the top of my head.
It might be a little wrong.
And you know, Jesus is coming back on this day.
And then when he didn't, it was called one of my favorite names for an event ever, the
great disappointment.
And then they coped with, well, he did come back, but it was like an heaven kind of thing.
Yeah.
If any Miller-Rach out there listening to me right now, I'm not sorry.
Come on, guys.
Yeah, that is weak sauce, man.
At least Harold Camping had the decency to get out of the business, right?
Right, he said, oh, my bad.
I was wrong.
But I mean, this was around in the 18th century, the 16th century.
Oh, yeah.
Right, over and over again.
If you actually go back and read, read some of the preaching
surrounding the crusades.
If you actually look at what the crusade preachers were preaching
for Peter the Hermiton, the crusade preachers were preaching.
we need to go and claim Jerusalem because...
once we've claimed Jerusalem Christ will return to it.
Wow, how 1948 of them?
Yes, exactly, right?
So this is all through Christian history, right?
That around the year 1000 people were selling
their land all over Europe.
Well, and little known fact as well,
which is surprising to me that this little known,
although it was little known to me until someone told us
to me, I guess by definition, but the reformation,
There was a huge amount of millen-
in fervor surrounding the Reformation. Like a lot of the earlier reformers really thought
that Jesus was about to come back. Like, Venn.
Right. Rome had been the great apostasy. Yeah. Yeah.
And now it had been revealed. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
And so this is a constant, right? And it goes all the way back. So,
right, we're going to be addressing the fact that this is not a cope, right?
There was no need for a cope. That means there's also need for
No need for preridism, by the way.
Preridism is just basically saying like,
oh yeah, Jesus kind of did
return during their lifetime in 78D.
Yeah.
Just kind of dumb, I'm sorry.
Right.
This is the first time I've said preridism
is kind of dumb on the air on this show.
So if they're a preridist left, sorry not sorry.
But...
That this is actually, we're going to talk about it is Christ,
what we commonly call Christ second adventer, second coming.
And we're going to talk about the actual biblical language.
This is baked into the cake.
This is built into the package.
This is in the New Testament, and specifically,
it's in the way the New Testament reads the Old Testament.
The New Testament sees this being in the Old Testament.
And once you understand the way that the New Testament is reading this out of the Old Testament,
once you understand it, there's no reason based on that to think that they thought this was
going to be a super short period of time. It could, right? But there is no link in this to any
any particular period of time.
And this is not just an issue of the
there being a bunch of messianic promises that Jesus didn't keep.
And so, well, he'll do that next time round, right?
That's not at all what's happening.
So the first thing, as we just mentioned,
that we have to kind of address is the language.
And we talk about Christ's second coming or his return.
Part of the problem with second coming
is a lot of people take that as if it's in like pair
L. Yeah. With Christ's
activity. Right. Right. So
like the whole plot of the
Omen 3 is that the Antichrist
played by Sam Neal, things that
Jesus is going to be born as a
baby again. I had to look
that up. 1981 supernatural
horror film. Well, that explains
why I didn't watch it. Yes. I
mean, I was. I was I that was
right around the time of my life.
when relevant to this episode, I was being traumatized by films like A Distant Thunder and Thief and the Leaf.
Yeah, there you go.
So the Open 3, I'm going to spoil for everyone.
The Etchie Christ, whose name is Damien Thorn in conspicuously.
Nice.
Is elected president of the United States.
Of course.
Wow, that's very liquid printed earth kind of stuff.
Yeah, so he could become the world ruler.
and but believes that Jesus...
This is gonna be born as a baby again.
And so, goes around trying to figure out what baby it is and killing babies.
That's basically the plot of the world.
I mean, I feel like I've read that somewhere already.
And the demons are all rotwilers.
It's a whole thing.
So, but it's always some kind of demon dog, isn't it?
Always a demon dog.
Yes, thanks son of Sam.
Anyway.
So, David Berkowitz did that to all of us.
So then the end of the movie is just a complete Deus Ex machina.
The end of the movie is just Jesus returns.
And it's like, duh, he wasn't going to be born as a baby idiot.
Wow.
Like that's how the movie ends.
You know, notably Larry Carr to the Chicago Tribune gave the film 1.5 stars
out of four praising Sam Niel's performance is the only thing the film had going for it.
Well, there you go.
Yes.
So, but yes, so, hopefully most people don't follow that language to think that there's some
kind of parallel there between Christ's activity and his second coming.
Although there are other, I won't go into them all in any level of detail because that
would get really tedious, I know, for even our audience.
There are a number of other works of fiction.
where that happens, or Jesus is born somewhere.
Well, and frankly, there are new religious movements
of the 20th century that claim that their leader is that.
Yeah, yeah.
They're kind of doing a Buddha riff.
Jesus reborn.
Like Dalai Lama Buddha riff.
Yeah, yeah.
So I mean, it is a thing, not just in fiction.
Right.
And so that makes sort of second coming, second advent.
little misleading as a way.
to speak, right? It's not that it's wrong to say that it's just that way of speaking
to be a little misleading. The other big one of course that I'm sure we've alluded to
on the show before is that Christ's return kind of implies that he left.
Right. Which I mean, he said, low, I am with you to the end of the age, which was not
like some weird sick joke.
You know.
Right. Right. Right. Right. Before the ascension. Right.
Immediately before the ascension in Matthew 28. Yeah.
To make very clear, his ascension to heaven was not him leaving. Yeah.
Right. It was not him like going away somewhere.
And part of so part of the problem here is,
is I think an over literal
reading of the ascension.
And you sometimes, especially if the Orthodox icon
of the ascension has it right.
A lot of other popular paintings
and depictions of the ascension,
it's sort of Jesus jumping up into the air.
Yes, right.
Or taking flight like Superman.
Yep.
I know of at least one Episcopal Church
where they release balloons.
Wow.
a sentient day?
Please no.
Oh my gosh.
Gotta limp.
But so, right, like, so this idea that Christ
sort of floated up into the air.
And so he's out in space or up there somewhere, right?
Like I said, that's a sort of goofy, weird,
over literal reading.
This is pretty much by the way, if you've noticed by being on the internet ever at all.
This is pretty much the atheist playbook for the Bible is you read the Bible in some kind
of goofy, super literal way and then point out how goofy it is.
Yeah.
And act like you've refuted the Bible in Christianity.
Right.
Yeah.
But so that's not what's actually being depicted in the ascension.
Right.
We've talked a lot.
before the show about Hebrew cosmology, right, where the Earth was imagined or
seemed to be round, flat, supported by pillars. What's under the pillars? Nothing.
There's water down there, but the pillars aren't on anything. And then there is a dome
of the sky.
right above. And God's throne, right? What we would call heaven, right, was in the heavens,
right, was above that, right? As we've talked about on this show many times, the Bible
is not making a, it never makes a scientific claim that that is true. Right. It's just
the Bible language.
is used. Right. The Bible speaks to people who that was their mental image of the cosmos.
And so just like God uses human languages, right, and any given human language has
has good and bad elements for conveying certain things, right? So also, God spoke to them in
in the language understand.
He didn't explain strength theory to Moses.
right? Like that's so this is how they view it this is how he talks to them. If
God was speaking to someone today or communicating something today to someone
giving some vision today he would do it in terms that they could
understand. He would use their language and he would have the universe depicted
the way they imagine it. Guess what? The way we 21st century folks imagine
the universe is not the
the universe really is either. What? I thought we were the most informed, the most
advanced, the final chapter of history. Thank you 19th century Germany. Yeah so we're
not either. Right so if God came and talked to us today about the universe the way it really is,
the way he understands it to be as its creator, we would not know what he is talking about.
He would have to communicate to us in our terms in order to communicate.
And God does that throughout the Scriptures.
So He did that with the disciples and the apostles.
And so when the disciples saw Christ go into the heavens carried by a cloud, this is why
the icon of the ascension, Orthodox icon, depicts Christ sitting on a cloud, not just flying.
This was communicating to them the scene we've talked about several times in Daniel 7 of the Son of Man coming before the ancient of days to be enthroned.
Right at his right hand.
Right so if you asked, right jump at the Tartus, go back to that day, right the angels say to the disciples, hey why are you still standing here?
You guys have work to do, right?
Stare it up to the sky and he said to them, hey, what happened? What did you just see?
Right, what they would tell you they just saw
Was Jesus being taken up to the throne of God and seated at his right hand
That's what they would tell you they saw
Yeah
Right
Is that what a GoPro attached to their head would have recorded?
No
Right? No, it is not. But that's not the way ancient people thought. Right? And God was able to communicate not only in words from human languages, but through human imagery, through human actions.
Right? When Christ cleanses the temple, he's communicating something through that action. Right?
So yes, this is and
This is one of those places where a certain group is going to be like,
why does he sound so kind of sending when he talks about this?
Because this stuff seems like it should be basic, but it's amazing how many people.
Not all I want to say, no, no, no, no, no, this means Jesus flew up into the sky
From the top of this mountain right at this time on this day and
And you need to affirm the accuracy of that historical fact, or you're not a Christian
or something, right?
Which is not how Christianity works, is not how the Scriptures work.
We've talked about this before.
If you need more of this, go back to our How to Read the Bible.
How and how not to read the Bible episode.
But so this also means that we can't interpret.
Right. That communication to the disciples who were there at the time seeing it was clear.
But we can't now go in through our 21st century scientific lens and try to interpret this
in terms of time and space, in terms of temporal and spatial categories. Right. Like by asking
the question, sorry Calvinist and the extra Calvinist to come, which I know I've
We've bashed a lot on the show.
But asking the question, where is Jesus or where is Jesus body now?
Show us you don't get it.
Right. That shows that you don't get it.
Jesus body is a physical body, but it's not somewhere in the material universe occupying material
space. It doesn't need to be.
God. Yeah. Right. Just like God's throne is not in a particular spot.
Occupying particular space. If you asked about the measurements of God's throne,
it would show that you don't get it. Right. We're not talking about a literal chair somewhere.
Right. Or this case, a literal throne chair yet somewhere.
God's rule, which is what God's throne.
represents, right, his reign, which is what him being seated represents, right, and is,
because there's not a difference between represents it is. His rule is everywhere.
He just thrown his everywhere, which leads the other thrown at his right hand is everywhere,
and the one seated in it is everywhere.
And so that means that Christ is present everywhere.
He's not absent from any place.
He hasn't gone away where he needs to come back.
Right?
Now that said, there is obviously something that changes at the time of the ascension.
Right.
was off.
also, by the way, as God, everywhere, during what we call his earthly life.
Yeah, I mean, there's, I, is it the, um, the anaphyruf, St.
Beas of the Great that says, you know, like in the grave of the body, but in
Hades, where the soul is God and in Paradise, where the thief and on the throne of
the Father and the Spirit was out, Christ, filling all things
itself on circumscribed. Now that's in, in even chrism, there's, you know,
that I think about it. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, he's, he's, and that's what he
with
dead right right exactly he's still all those things all those places all at once you know right
but but uh he was present in a different sense obviously with his bodily presence
right so together with the disciples and this is a little bit brain breaking
Right, in terms of if you try to
figure out how it works. So don't try. We're talking about God. But this is parallel to, right?
Remember, we're told over and over again, especially in St. John's Gospel that Christ's body is
the temple. Right? And if you look at the Old Testament, the Old Testament is completely clear
that God is everywhere. If I go to the depths of the Chio, there he is. If I go to the top
Thank you very much.
mountains there he is if I go right, God is everywhere. And it's also equally clear that he is
present in a special way among his people in the Tabernacle and in the temple.
So when St. John in his prologue says the word became flesh and Tabernacled among us,
and then when he talks about from very early in his gospel,
I destroy this temple. I'll be...
rebuild it in three days and say,
John adds the parathetical comment.
He was speaking of his body just in case you didn't get it.
Right.
He's drawing a direct parallel to this.
Right. It's, it's not that all of a sudden now,
this, the, the logos of God, right.
The divine logos is only present.
So where Christ's body is?
Right.
Yeah.
And no longer present any of the other places.
He is still present all the other places.
But he is present in this special way.
Allah the Temple.
Allah the Tabernacle.
Right.
Allah any fiyafani in the Old Testament for that matter,
among his disciples.
And it's that kind of person.
Kind of...
presence, that immediate bodily presence where they could look with their physical eyes and
see his face, right, and touch him, etc. That is what changes at the ascension.
Right. So the way you're the mode in which he is present changes.
Yeah, which I mean, even if you just look at what he says at the ascension, that would seem
obvious like okay they're not seeing him bottle
any more and yet he says I'm with you always the end of the age so okay that's
pretty straightforward. Right and don't get yourself tied into not trying to
figure it out though. Right the the place where this is described as much as
it can be described to us humans right is in the
appropriately enough since I just referenced the early parts of St. John's
and the latter parts of St. John's Gospel, particularly surrounding
Christ's prayers in the presence of the disciples and then his prayers for the disciples before
his arrest, that we read at great length in that first gospel reading on Holy Thursday,
where Christ talks about the Holy Spirit, that the key change that happens at the ascension
is that rather than Christ being present in their midst,
in
this physical way, this mode of physical presence, where they can see him with their eyes,
hear him with their ears, touch him with their hands, that he is now going to be present
among them in the Holy Spirit.
The Holy Spirit who is going to come after the ascension makes Christ present.
And so this language.
that then permeates the rest of the New Testament,
becomes a stumbling block for a lot of people in modern translations,
because we get this word spiritually,
where the spirit in spiritual or spiritually isn't capitalized.
Yeah, and it sort of means not real.
Yeah
like some ephemeral way, or some allegorical or analogical way.
Like being spiritual but not religious?
Yeah, just some vague, you know, no, that's true spiritually now.
Right.
And that means not really.
And again, in the text, this is quite the opposite.
In the text, this is capital S.
This is the-
Holy Spirit. Right. And so in debates, and yes, we're going to be touching on the Eucharist
here. So especially in these debates, but in others as well, this dichotomy is drawn
between spiritual and real. Right. And again, the Eucharist is a clear place. We use debates.
Well, these groups Roman Catholic.
Orthodox Lutherans believe in the real presence of Christ of the Eucharist, and Calvinists,
who at least the handful who follow Calvin believe in the spiritual presence. Or, and maybe
even some other Protestant groups, we'll use that same language, even though their meaning
is even more ephemeral than cowlands.
And yes, spiritual is not as opposed to...
because the Holy Spirit is real and the Holy Spirit is God.
Right. Right.
And so a place where we see, I think,
or a good example of this issue in interpretation,
is when people are interpreting passages
wherever two or three are gathered in my name,
There I will be in the midst of them.
Yep.
And a lot of interpretations of this are just,
Hey man, two or three Christians,
some pretzels in a acoustic guitar, right?
There's Jesus hanging out with us.
That's not what it's saying.
At all.
And the key part there is,
what does it mean to gather in Christ's name?
Right. That's not just a random phrase. That's not just like the purpose. Like, hey, we
gathered this week to rewatch Breaking Bad next week. We're gathering to talk about
Jesus, right? That's not just the topic. This is picking up the language from the Old
testament going all the way back into Genesis.
of calling on the name of the Lord.
And to call on the name of the Lord
didn't just mean to say Yahweh out loud, right?
Calling on the name of the Lord meant worship
and specifically it meant sacrifice.
Right.
And you can read this all in verse,
I will take the code of salvation
and call upon the name of the Lord.
Yeah.
Yeah. Which we sing, you know, as a communion
him at a number of the feet.
of the Church.
Right.
So this is referring to the Eucharist.
The Eucharist is gathered to celebrate the Eucharist Christ is there with them.
And how is he there?
He's there in the power of the Holy Spirit, the core of the Orthodox divine liturgy.
This is why for us the epicoleases is the most important part, more important than the
words of institution, more important than anything else.
Right?
Because it is at that epicoleases where just as the Holy Spirit made Christ present in the
Whoa.
of the Theotokos, at the Annunciation, the Holy Spirit makes Christ present on the altar
in the Eucharist.
And so again, right?
Someone will say, well, wait a minute.
Isn't Christ everywhere?
And we'll say again, yes.
Great.
like God was everywhere the Old Testament but a-
especially in the temple, but especially in the tabernacle, but especially in the
person of Jesus of Nazareth, but especially of the Eucharist.
So those aren't at odds with each other. If you understand this in the
Scriptures. Okay. So that...
That means, hypothetically, you could describe every Eucharistic celebration as another coming
of Christ.
Of Christ again becoming present with us.
And so when we talk about what is commonly called Christ second coming, we again need to be
be more specific and make some distinctions.
because what we're talking about that comes at the end before the day of judgment, etc.,
is this unique event, this unique coming of Christ.
And so the New Testament uses a few different words to explain this.
by the way, for...
The people listening live
This may not be relevant to the people listening to their recording but for people listening live
Yes, I am in a wind tunnel where they're testing aircraft engines
Speaking of live listeners that we actually have someone listening from Scotland's tonight so good on you staying up late. Yeah
Enjoying your beautiful temperatures. Yeah, yeah
So, um...
So the most common term and the Greek term that you're probably familiar with, because
to deal with sort of the misleading nature of talking about Christ's return or his second
coming, a lot of times if you're reading, you know, high popular into academic literature,
They'll just use the term parusia, untranslated from Greek to refer.
to what we call Christ Second Coming.
Yeah, which is, I don't know.
It's kind of a weird flex.
I think.
But yeah, okay.
I mean, like I said, I kind of get why they do it.
The English translations don't really do justice
to the word, but yeah, sometimes it's just weird.
Because you still have to explain it.
Yeah, you still then have to explain it.
If you care whether people who read your stuff
understand you, yeah.
Well, you know, a lot of people make...
a good market out of mudding the waters to make them appear deep, right? Like, you're
making deliberately semi-intelligable, so everyone just assumes you're smart, and nobody
wants, it's like the emperors new clothes, nobody wants to admit that they didn't get it.
I'm not talking about anyone's work in particular. I'm saying sometimes that happens.
Here, I was thinking of post-structural literary theorists, but, you know. Oh, there, there.
You're going to be able to do it.
I suffered a lot of that stuff when I was in undergrad.
I was like, what?
What?
Yeah.
I don't really have a good apology for Jacques Derrida.
Like, no.
For so many reasons.
I mean, yeah.
He was less fascist than Heidegger, but way worse read.
Like, that's saying something with old Mart.
Anyway.
All right.
Potosia, fancy equipment.
Potosia.
It's not actually that fancy agree, Quartz.
It's another one of those though that doesn't super work to just
etymologically pull it apart because it means like being alongside or being
with, I mean, that sort of works, sort of works, but.
Kind of, but you know, butterfly.
Yeah, right.
Breakfast.
Yeah.
So it's pretty commonly used in St. Paul.
I'm just kidding.
Jack Van APU, a few references that you can slow this down
and look up later if you're so inclined.
First Corinthians 15, verse 23, 16, verse 17.
Second Corinthians 7, verses 6 and 7.
10, verse 10.
Philippians 1, verses 26.
2, verse 12.
First S.S.S.S.L.O.D.E.N.2 19-3-13-4-15-5-23.
Second S.S.S.S.L.O.D.E.N.2 vs. 1-8-9.
Except he could do it faster.
And from memory.
He's a big... he's a rope.
So I have to give them that.
Yeah, and not all of those, by the way, as we're going to mention in a minute, have to do with Christ's return.
Yeah.
Some of those are other uses of the word.
Some are just about other people and not in a particular like special moment.
They just, it means, and so and so showed up.
Yeah.
Or was there or, yeah.
So it's also other places in the New Testament.
Get ready for another list.
Matthew 24, verse 3, verse 27, 37, 39, James 5, verses 7 and 8.
Second Peter 1, 16, 3, verse 4, and 12.
Verse John 2, verse 28.
I'll use the term paracetia.
So in terms of what it means, terms are really nailing down what it means.
Normally, almost 100% of the time, if you want to know what a Greek word means in the
New Testament, you need to see what it's used to translate in the Greek Old Testament.
Because literally a lot of the New Testament writers are thinking in Hebrew or Aramaic
and writing in Greek.
Right, so they're kind of it's kind of a clunky
They're translating in their head. Yeah, yeah, right and this is where a lot of New Testament interpretation goes wrong is
jumping right into lexica of general Greek and
classical Greek
without referencing the Greek Old Testament tradition
So that is almost a hundred percent of the time
uh... the uh...
the thing that you need to do.
I'm gonna go ahead, this is gonna get a bunch of people, man.
But I don't think I've really ticked anybody off yet tonight.
So here we go.
Keeney Greek or coin a Greek,
as it's sometimes called, doesn't exist and isn't a thing.
Dun, dun, dun.
I feel like I should have some kind of jingle ready
for whenever you say that kind of thing.
It's biblical Greek.
Someone get me a budget for good soundboard.
It's Hellenistic Greek written by Semitic language speakers.
That's all it is.
Yeah, it's Greek as a second language.
It is not a separate dialect.
It is not a separate language.
It doesn't exist outside the Greek scriptures.
And the turgical Greek is just the continuation of that.
Using that same pattern, which is overlaid.
But here we're, if you haven't studied...
Hebrew and Aramaic, you can't understand it properly. Now our Greek
listenership is picking up pitchforks and torches. But deal with it, it's true.
It is verifiably true. How dare you? How dare you? If you want to prove me wrong, give
me an example of Keny Greek outside of the Greek Scriptures. Because everybody
He also writes at that time,
Fylo, Josephus, and Greek.
It's not the same dialect.
Yeah, I mean, mostly, most of the time now,
actually you hear people refer to it as biblical Greek.
Like I'm taking biblical Greek.
Yeah.
The common key-need means common.
It became the common Greek because it was biblical Greek.
It was the other way.
The same way
that the Latin vulga was not like vulgar Latin
at the time Saint Jerome made the translation.
It became the common Latin due to Saint Jerome's translation.
Anyway, so now that's irritated a bunch of people.
Now I got some Latin folks mad at me too
with that last little bit, I bet.
So all that said, wherever I said almost 100% of the time,
This is the exception, Parasia.
Yeah, because parasyah gets used a bunch in the Christian Old Testament the Greek Old Testament
Never once used for God
What do I mean by that? I mean all the places in the Hebrew Bible as
They're getting translated into the Greek Old Testament tradition all the places in the Hebrew Bible that talk about
God visiting his people the day of the Lord.
God appearing, God coming to Abraham, God coming to Mount Sinai, God coming on the
last day in judgment, none of them use the term parosia to refer to it. So there
is no direct connection to using that Greek term to refer to anything
related.
to the end of days, the last judgment, et cetera.
So this is the one case where you do have to go and look at how it's used in the Greek
surrounding, particularly in the Roman world, in the first century AD when St. Paul and
the New Testament writers are using it.
And the way it was used was to refer to someone
being present in person.
They're then visiting or they're arrival.
St. Paul uses it this way to describe himself
coming to visit one of the churches.
Yeah, my part was here.
Right.
So it's being there in person.
He makes this count.
the contrast between, oh, you know, he seemed bold in his
epistles, but then when he was here in person, when he was
when he baricia, right, then something else, right.
So often it was used to refer to the visit of the Roman
Emperor or another official Senator, a general, a governor.
And the idea was sort of their rule.
is already present.
Right, so the understanding of the Roman Empire,
right, Caesar, even though they believed him to be divine,
or at least be possessed by a divine spirit,
he was only in one physical place at a time.
Right.
Nevertheless, Caesar's rule or his dominion or his power extended over the whole Empire.
So that dominion or that rule of Caesar was already in Thessalonica, but then if
Caesar comes to Thessalonica in person, right, that would be his parosea, his sort of bodily presence.
And so this makes it a particularly good word for what we're describing here.
because remember the New Testament writers do not see Christ as being absent.
Right his kingdom his rule his authority is here and everywhere
But there comes a day when he is again present in person the way he was
Before his disciples on that mountain in Galilee before the right before the ascension
So, part of the policy is helpful in that way.
There are a couple of other words, though, that are used in the New Testament to describe
this.
One of them is epiphanea, i.e. epiphany, which means appearing or manifestation.
Thanks for watching.
See you next time.
one we can and should go back to the Greek Old Testament tradition, right? And there
we see this one gets used all the time regarding God. For example, in the Theophonies when
he appears to Abraham, this is the word that's used, right? When he manifests himself to Abraham
over and over again. And of course the
offene is built out of the word of
piphany, right?
It's just got the, the OS, appended instead of the preposition.
But it's also importantly not just used for those sort of general theophanies, but epiphania
is used in at least a few places to describe the day of the Lord.
that other day of the Lord God is going to appear.
Yeah, right.
And those are in...
for example, Joel, Joel 2, verse 11, and 31, and Malachi 3, verse 23. So you see
those are fairly late Old Testament books in their Greek translations. And then
Saint Paul picks up this language. This is where it's often translated in English
his glorious appearing, or his appearing in glory, or the appearance of his glory,
depending on how the English translators.
Joseph to render it. And those are in 2 Timothy 4 verse 1 and 8, 2 Thessalonians 2 verse 8,
and Titus 2 verse 13. For example, use that language. So again, it's not that Christ is absent
and becomes present again, it's Christ is present, but not in a visible way. And he appears,
or manifest.
himself. And then relatedly the language of Apocalypse, right? Apocalypse. It's the obvious
English transliteration, which means to reveal or uncover. And this is used repeatedly in the
the Greek Old Testament to talk about when God reveals himself to the prophets.
to commission them.
So for example, 1 Samuel 3 verses 7 and 21,
when he reveals himself to Samuel, the prophet,
2 Samuel 7 verse 27, he reveals himself to David,
AMS III verse 7 talks about him revealing himself to the prophets in general.
This language is used, previous episode,
we talked at length about Balaam, son of Bior.
he tries to curse Israel instead.
ends up blessing Israel, and that's because in the Greek text God reveals himself to him
in Numbers 22, verse 31, 24, verse 4, and 16. And this language is used to describe this
last day and what happens with Christ that Christ is revealed in 2 Thessalonians 1, verse
1 Corinthians 1 verses 7 and 8 and 1 Peter 4 verse 13 with his idea that Christ is still
But his presence is in some way veiled and then gets uncovered.
Yeah, which, that's one of the reasons I like this particular word to describe what's happening because like he's there, but you know,
like you said, veiled and then okay, now he's unveiled. He's not any more there, but he becomes a parent.
He reveals himself.
Right, right. And so you could see
The other thing that this
connection through the word apocalyptic brings out is that there's this overlap between
the prophetic vision of the prophets in the Old Testament and the appearance of Christ
at his quote unquote second advent.
in terms of what is seen and who is seen and how he is.
scene. And this then likewise dovetails with one of the Orthodox churches called
Division of Christ and his uncreated glory, which is an experience given to certain
saints by God. But one of the key elements of it, according to St. Gregory
polymos is that they are seeing him with their eyes.
Yeah, it's not just some kind of mental vision or
vision, right?
They're seeing with their eyes
which means this is the kind of presence,
this is the kind of revealing
that is going to happen for everyone
on the last day, right?
It is going to constitute
what we call Christ return or second coming.
All right, well, that's been our first half
so we're going to take a little break
and we will be right back with the Lord of Spirit.
podcast.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and
Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
This is Andrew Williams. My new book from Object to Icon, the struggle for
for spiritual vision in a pornographic world.
Shows how we can stop a-
objectifying others and instead see the spiritual reality in everyone we encounter.
From Object to Icon, it's now available at store.enginethec.com.
A new addition of the Good Samaritan, of first of its kind, catacism, written specifically
for young people to communicate the unchanging truths of the Orthodox faith, is now available
at store.enginethec.com
We're back now with the Lord.
of spirits. The father Andrew Stephen Damick and father Stephen DeYoung. If you have a question,
call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, that was pretty short and sweet for commercials and we didn't even have to listen to one with
your voice on it. So, thankfully. Yeah, I don't know how that first book is. It's brand
news. Of course I haven't read it. Yeah, it's brand news. The light-full accent. Oh, yeah,
Yeah, yeah, yeah, I got to use an audio.
book to pick up. Right? Yeah, I got to talk to him a little bit as we were working on the book.
Initially, you know, when we were sort of starting with, they're not to accept it. And,
and yeah, he's got a great, great accent. An actual Englishman.
Yes, I'm sure we sound like warbling geese to him, but we find his accent delightful.
It's true. Although, you know, I've noticed that when people from other countries, especially
British people do an American accent a lot of the time they just kind of default to Texas
Like that's what an American accent is there is the cowboy thing, but the other thing is they sort of overpronounce
That sound yeah, right because they don't do that sound they have like the chimpanzee
So if they're doing America it's like chimpanzee
Nancy which is kind of a little Brooklyny I think yeah, I listen
I want to do a lot of Dr. Who audio dramas and when they've got British actors doing
Americans I feel judged.
I have to.
It's judging.
Come on big finish.
We accept it.
I mean, if there's anything American needs to do it's repent.
It'll be a little.
Yeah.
Well, welcome back everybody.
is the second half for the Lord of Spirits and
We're ready to take your calls if you got something you want to talk about.
If you feel that you're about to be raptured, call in.
We'd love to talk to you on your way up.
I explained to you that you're not.
It's right.
It's 855 AF radio.
That's 8552372346.
So right.
Okay.
So we talked about this idea of appearing.
Right.
You know, and the various rights appearing.
Not people disappearing.
Yes.
Right.
Exactly.
Yeah, you know, the various words
that are used for that in the Scriptures and of course appearance of God and all this kind of thing.
So what is this then about a second appearing, right, that there's two of them? What is that all
about? Like, why does that need to be a thing? As you said earlier, did Jesus come and like, oh,
oh, actually, you know, I'll do the rest of that stuff later. My, you know, like, what's going on?
and why is there, where are there two?
Right, well so.
This is part of that false construct again, right, which is this idea that first of all there was sort of one uniform view and ancient Judaism.
And that that one uniform view was the Messiah is going to show up one day.
He is then immediately during his lifetime going to inaugurate the world to come.
Yeah
And everything was the right.
And the resurrection of the dead and eternity and all of that, right?
And if you've been listening to this show for a while, you know already that's a bunkum,
right?
Like, first of all, there was no uniform view by quote unquote Judaism in the first century.
There are Judaism's at best.
Some people have even said you...
shouldn't even talk about Judaism's,
because that implies more organization than there was.
Right? Like Judaism's makes people think
that they were like different denominations
or something, right?
That they had like, internal structures
and hierarchies and stuff,
which some Jewish groups had and some didn't, right?
And those folks say you should really just talk about
the religious beliefs and practices of Jewish people
during the period.
Right.
Which is a different kind of approach.
So the idea that there was this monolithic view and that therefore the disciples would
have to figure out how to defend the reality of what Jesus of Nazareth did over against
that monolithic view doesn't hold water.
Yeah.
Right.
So before we dive deep into that, we actually hope you have someone calling from
Well, his phone is from Texas.
His, I'm not sure if he's from Texas, but...
Are you applying, he's using a stolen burner phone?
Well, you know, we recently got a phone for one of our kids,
and then the kid calls me and it says that it's in Utah.
I'm like, wait, what?
Somehow, his phone number is from Utah, I don't know.
Your kid's flirting with Mormonism, Father.
I know. Or maybe just the phone is Mormon, you know?
that could be.
So, yes, anyway, we have Paul calling from Texas maybe. So, Paul, are you there with us?
I am a little father. Good evening. Welcome to Lord of Spirits podcast. Are you indeed in Texas or
as you just your fellow Roman Texas public of Texas? Yeah. I indeed am in Texas. Alrighty. Well,
we have recalled the Alamo. Well, then we can be a piece. Okay, good.
Okay, so my question is kind of a question that I'm hoping can provide some contra
even after the episodes about spirit and
How much that's helped I'm still a little bit muddy on some things. Okay. I recently
Learned in reference to when Christ confirmed that Saint John the Baptist came in the spirit of Elijah
That that's not a Elijah's
return that apparently was
profiled. I've just not
about until recent Sundays.
school either and that some of the church fathers believe that both Elijah and Enoch could
be the two witnesses in Revelation.
Now I only reference that to ask y'all maybe contrast a bit more what being present in spirit
means as opposed to being bodily presence because I do know that Pratkyolthena show called
Messiah, it seemed like they kind of
the idea of somebody being, you know, returning in spirit, like as though Christ returned, but he returned
in some other human individual, and that's his return. Yeah. Which obviously isn't correct, but I was so
muddy on the waters that even though I knew it was wrong, I was still really confused. It was an enjoyable
show either way, but yeah, if you could just please explain that a little bit more to give some
contract. Right, I mean so when Christ return
it is Christ, right? And, you know, I mean, it says right at the end of the
gospels, you're gonna see him come in the manner which you're seeing him as
sent. Right? So, I mean, that's one of the things that's kind of funny about all
these people who say, you know, oh, this is the second coming of Jesus. I'm like,
well, but like we have pretty clear description of what that's gonna be like,
from the angels who speak to the apostles.
right after the ascension, right?
So it's not gonna be some weird secret.
Or, you know, but yeah, I mean,
I think it's an interesting question, right?
That John the Baptist is easy Ligia,
but not, he's not the second coming of a Ligia, right?
It's not this.
What I thought he was before my priest elaborated on that,
I was very surprised.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, there is this tradition that he and Enoch
or good.
to be the two witnesses that appear at the end, you know, before the second coming, for
the second manifestation of Christ, I'm trying to see, I have to revise my own language,
you know, because I'm sitting here with Father Stephen digitally. So yeah, I don't know,
Father, you want to help Paul and Texas out here?
Yeah, yeah. So, and back in the episode we did about Saint John the Four and we talked
about the relationship between.
Him and Elijah and how Elijah is more like a patron saint to him right and the good idea of
the mantle of
Elijah right um and so
yeah the
the two witnesses being
Enoch and Elijah in Revelation is picked up actually from second-tep old Jewish litur.
that talks about in a kind of a lie, because they're the two figures in the old
testament who don't die.
They return in some capacity, right, and either finish their life or do something.
In the case of ENEC, a lot of times that's connected to.
There's one of the very commonplace things in Second Temple Jewish literature and
that you testament is...
this connection between the days of Noah,
which Enic is in that lead up to when God is going to destroy the world,
judge the world under Noah, and the end of this age.
And so it's considered sort of particularly appropriate that Enic would come back in that context.
text. Right.
The book of Enoch and other in-knockic literature that's written in the Second Temple period
is really playing with this idea that they believed they were living in the Great Tribulation
following the exile, that they were coming to the end of the age, and so it was like,
oh, well, these prophecies of Enoch from the last time the world got this bad,
they're particularly relevant again now.
And you even see this coming in in the new testament.
Right, when it talks about Christ glorious appearing
and it talks about, you know, as in the days of Noah,
people were being married and given in marriage
and all these things were at, right,
there are these sort of similar comparisons, right.
But, yeah, that it's the actual people
reincarnated in some sense, right,
is taking it a little too literally, right.
that this is about a sort of spiritual dynamic.
of people prophesying and living and speaking in certain situations, the parallels between
those situations and those people.
Yeah, I don't think it's, I mean, I think it's okay to say, like for instance, the
Appolitikian that we sing for the Aprofitalias calls him the second forerunner of Christ God's
coming to us, right, which is in line with that tradition of him being one of these two
witnesses.
And I think it's okay to say, a liar's will come before the end.
How exactly that plays out?
I don't.
really think we know, you know, is that going to be him showing up on Earth again,
him him, or people acting in the way that he did? You know, like, I don't think we totally know.
Right. It is possible that literally Elijah and Nina could show up in some capacity, right?
eschatologically. We're not ruling that out. Yeah.
But I don't think it literally happening is demanded by what's being said in Scripture, either.
Yeah.
Okay.
So you in contrast to Christ bodily returning, he himself, not somebody else in some other way,
What would it be fair to say, kind of like what father,
Andrew Stephen Damick just said, that maybe coming in the spirit of somebody is more.
about behaving in their mantle of their pattern of action,
like the way they operate, the way they think,
the way they speak.
Yeah.
That's kind of a short way to take it.
I would go back and listen to the episode about
St. John the Four, or we'd go into that in more detail.
In the way that, like, you know,
St. John says he isn't Elijah.
And then at another point,
Christ says that he was.
Right.
The...
the whole thing.
The episode is it isn't in different senses, right?
The episode if you're looking it up, if you haven't listened to it yet, is called Make
Straight the Paths for our God.
So I will check that out tomorrow.
Thank you very much, fathers.
You're welcome.
Thank you very much for calling in.
All right.
Why don't we talk about Psalm 110?
I mean, the New Testament does all the time.
Yeah.
So yeah, so we're getting it back into, right, this idea that so not only is there no
sort of monolithic Judaism that has one view of exactly what the Messiah is going to do
when he comes. If you go back and listen to our Messiah episode, you'll know that during
the Second Temple period, a lot of different Jewish groups were expecting multiple Messiahs.
Oh yeah, right. Right. And not just, I mean, apropos to the collar, right? Not just somebody
thought, well, Elijah's going to come and then the Messiah's going to come. But, priestly Messiah,
King Lee Messiah, right? They had a
a lot of different views, right?
And so there wasn't some need imposed
by necessity to keep their movement alive
in the face of some embarrassment
for the New Testament writers to come up with this idea
of the Messiah coming twice, right?
So where then did they get it, right?
And so we're going to talk about some of the scriptures of the Hebrew Bible and then the Greek Old Testament tradition from which
they get it. And the first of those is as Father Andrew mentioned, Psalm 110, 109 in the Greek.
This is the most quoted Hebrew Bible slash Old Testament text in the New Testament over and over again.
Book of Hebrews is just a meditation on it gets quoted everywhere. So it's critically important
If the major theme of the New Testament is that Jesus of Nazareth is the Messiah, this is the key text that's being used to describe what that means throughout the New Testament.
And also, I know we talked about this way, way back in the long ago time.
Like in early episodes, like in the first 10 episodes.
During one of the episodes, I remember we talked about...
why we say Yahweh live on air. And one of the key reasons we gave is that the way
English Bible translations do both Yahweh as Lord and other words that mean
Lord as Lord makes it hard to follow some passages. Yeah and Psalm 110 verse
one is sort of ground zero for that.
which is of course in English is usually the Lord said to my Lord. Yeah, but it's in Hebrew, it's
Yahweh said to Adonai. Yeah, the Lord said to my Lord, sit at my right hand until I make your
enemies your footstool and then verse two talks about ruling in the midst of your enemies.
which is kind of before and after the ascension.
Right, right.
Reading this, right, Christ quotes this of course to the Pharisees and scribes
and says after giving them the first verse says
if
The Messiah is David's son. How does he call him Lord?
Right and it says they went away discouraged unable to answer him well one easy answer would have been this isn't talking about the Messiah
right?
But that was not an option for them apparently, right?
So this shows there was broad acceptance that this soul is talking about the Messiah, that
the Adinae here is the Messiah, right?
It's the Lord Messiah.
And what does it say?
Here the Lord Messiah is enthroned, is enthroned at the right hand of God.
he's not enthroned to
rule over the now perfectly justified and purified earth. Over a time of abundance, he's
enthroned to rule in the midst of his enemies. His enemies are still out there. They're still
out there causing trouble for some period of time. Right. And then at the end of that
period of time, something else happens and in verse 5, right? And this is another
play.
where you read it in English and it says,
the Lord is at your right hand.
And just reading that quickly in English,
that may sound like, well, is the you me?
Like God is always at my right hand?
Or if you look at it, the Lord there is not Yahweh.
The Lord there is at an eye again.
Right, so Christ.
Right, so it's the Lord.
Messiah is at your meaning Yahweh's right hand, right? That's where he was. It was what said at my right hand, right?
And then it describes him destroying the enemies.
Yeah. Shatter kings on the day of his wrath.
On the day of his wrath, the day, right? So there is this period of time between the enthronement of the Messiah to rule and the final judgment,
the final decision.
of the enemies. There's a period of time. And there's nothing here to suggest that it's short, long, medium, right?
Nothing here to suggest length.
Another passage from the Psalms. Psalm 2.
Why in the King James, why does the heathen rage? Why did the heathen rage? I just did a great word.
and the nation's plot in vain.
But in verse 2, they plot against Yahweh and his Messiah or his Christ in the Greek.
Yeah, against the Lord and is anointed as it says in the ESV.
And verse 3 makes clear that this isn't talking about David.
Right, because it says, let us burst their bonds apart and cast away their courts from us,
which these are the nations.
Yeah.
Yeah, David is not in bondage to God.
David didn't rule over the Gentiles.
Right.
David didn't rule over the nations.
He ruled over Israel.
Right.
Yep.
So it's the Messiah who's going to come to rule over the nations.
Right.
The ultimate Messiah, the ultimate son of David.
Who's going to do that?
And then in verse 4, he who sits in the heavens laughs and the Lord at an eye holds them
in derision.
So this is...
the two of them laughing.
Yeah, kind of.
And sharing a joke between themselves.
Yes.
At the kings and the rulers of the nations.
And then in verse seven, when you get the coronation language, it's Yahweh said to me,
you are my son today.
I have begotten you.
So this is the Messiah's coronation, right, his enthronement.
Right?
Is this...
Sun, verse nine is interesting.
The Hebrew, the original Hebrew has, you shall break.
Well, okay.
The Hebrew as it's typically vowel pointed
in the mass that are at a Hebrew text
has you shall break them with a rod of iron.
The Greek has you shall rule them with a rod of iron.
And you can get rule instead of break
based on different vowel marks.
There you go.
Nice little.
and make your deep cut.
there. Yeah. So again, you have this period of time depicted where the Messiah is
reigning at the right hand of God and there are still these enemies who at
some ultimate point are going to throw off their shackles, see battle of Armageddon,
et cetera, right, and then be defeated, right, by the Messiah. We won't go into
too much detail on Daniel.
seven again just because we keep coming back to it over and over and over again.
Go see our Son of Man episode if you're really going to do all that again.
But Daniel 7, Son of Man is enthroned the right hand of the ancient of days.
In verses 13 and 14 it talks about how he's enthroned over the nations but then
there's this period of time between his enthronement and the saints taking
possession of the kingdom and the beasts being judged.
Alright, so there's this period of time.
See...
the millennium episode recently, the Son of Man episode, we go more into that, into Daniel 7,
and the details of that there. But again, there's this period of time, right? This period of time.
And it's that period of time, excuse me, that we talked about in the millennium episode, but that also
So represents why that ultimate judgment by the Messiah is described as a
second coming, right, because it's after his enthronement and this period of time.
And so the fact that Christ is seated at the right hand of God, the Father, right,
becomes an important statement in the New Testament and then subsequently in the
and in Christian theology.
So the first kind of...
place it comes up is in the Gospels in Matthew 26, 64, Mark 14, verse 62, Luke 22, verse 69.
These are all parallel passages. These are all Jesus speaking to the high priest.
Right. He says, from now on, you'll see the Son of Man sitting at the right hand of power
or sitting at the right hand. Right. Which makes angels super unhappy when he says.
Right. But this Son of Man sitting at the right hand, right, and coming to judge. Right. That's,
That's the important.
part here, right? This is a thing. So I know friend of the show, Bart Irman, based on
the, shall we say, less than nuanced way he made, has made some of his arguments in his
popular level books, has convinced a lot of people that the title Son of Man was not referring
to any kind of heavenly or eschatological figure ever.
Right? So there's a...
time when people took any time to phrase Son of Man appeared in the New Testament. It was referring
directly to like Daniel 7 and all everything, right? Obviously, you're going to be able to find
exceptions to that, right? So obviously we have to say, well, no, not always, right? But due to the
way Bartirman and others, Bartirmer just was well known one and the friend of the show, the way he
He made that argument.
He's now could be.
It's a lot of people that just like it never means that.
Well, here's three examples, parallel passage,
where it clearly means that.
Yeah, and Bart, you know, you're a friend of the show.
Why don't you go listen to our son of man episode?
Or just call in.
Yeah, call in.
I would love to hear.
Yeah, he talked to me so.
He will jump.
If a friend of the show, Bart Irman, ever calls the show,
he will go straight to the front of the line.
Yeah.
Why not?
We will immediately take the call.
We will devote the rest of the show
to talking to him if necessary,
as long as he wants it.
talk. Well, that is the biggest invitation you've ever given on this stuff. Yes, yes,
and I mean it. So then, so then after the ascension, what we find through the rest of
the New Testament are just repeated references. Some of them almost seeming off hand, right?
You're going to be in the next video.
to Christ, the fact that Christ, that Jesus is seated at the right hand of God.
So here's another Jack van Impelist, Mark 16, verse 19, Acts 2, verse 33, 5, verse 31, 7, verses 55 and 56,
Romans 8, verse 34, Ephesians 1, verse 20, Colossians 3, verse 1, Hebrews 1, verse 3, and 8, verse 1,
10 verse 12, 12 verse 2, first Peter 3 verse 22.
Right, those all are.
to Christ being seated at the right hand of God.
And this, of course, is part of the Nicene Creed,
right, that we recite not only that Christ
descended into heaven, but that he is seated
at the right hand of the Father.
And so when this is, when we confess this,
we'll make reference to this, there are a number
of levels here, right?
The first level, the most immediate, maybe level,
is that we're identifying Jesus as the Messiah,
by identifying him with his existing Messiah traditions
of the Messiah, the Lord Messiah being enthroned
at the right hand of God.
But this also, the fact that Christ
is enthroned at the right hand of God,
speaks to the activity of Christ
as the ruler over the nations, meaning over the world,
which is a rule that he shares with the saints.
His role is high priest.
As you can see in the references I just gave from Hebrews,
which he shares with the saints as priests.
So there's an activity here.
There's something Christ is doing.
And so this period of time is not just like a pause.
It's not just like, well, Jesus did half of the Messiah
stuff and then took a break.
And then he's going to come back and do the rest of it.
Right?
Right.
it
This is part and parcel of what the Messiah does.
He rules in the midst of his enemies for a time.
He rules over the nations while his enemies, these spiritual enemies,
these kings and rulers of the earth, these beasts and Daniel are still active in the world.
This is part of what the Messiah was going to do.
Jesus is doing it.
This is the idea here.
This is necessary according to the Old Testament.
And so it requires that there be these two
different manifestations of Christ, one which culminates in his enthronement, and then
the second one where he appears to render judgment on the enemies.
All right.
So this has been the second half.
It's actually very brief.
It appears the first one for us.
But yeah, for us, it's true.
It's true.
I mean, there are some other shows.
There are some much more cons-
size shows on ancient phrase radio. But this is not one of them.
This was originally going to be a one hour show.
Hey, that is true. This was in its original conception. But I don't think we've ever
done with the exception of some of your little brief ones that you've done,
like when I've been traveling or something like that, that you did so.
I don't think we've ever had one that's actually been under an hour.
So yeah. All right, well we're going to go ahead and take our second break and we'll be back
with a third hand.
Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Hi, do you know me?
I'm Father Stephen DeYoung.
My new book, Apocrypha and Introduction
to Extra Biblical Literatures, now available.
A lot of Christians today divide.
ancient Jewish and Christian literature into two categories.
What's in the Bible? What's not in the Bible?
Christian East, however, has traditionally had a third category, a middle category,
books that are read privately in the home.
A Greek word for that is apocryphal.
These texts from the centuries before and the centuries after the incarnation of Christ,
that go beyond even the larger canons of Orthodox and Roman Catholic churches,
Reveal to us the religious world and theological framework of the
apostles and early church fathers. In this book Apocrypha I survey these works
which connect elements of liturgy, scripture, iconography,
patristic writings. Familiarity with these works will enhance readers
understanding of the breadth and depth of the Orthodox Christian faith.
Buy a copy of Apocrypha and introduction to extrabiblical literature at
store.anxionfaith.com. That's store.anxionfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and father Steven DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
I mean, why are we advertising that book?
I mean, it's been out for, that was awful four months.
I think it's because we said something
about the first one not having first commercial break,
not including YouTube.
He's like, well, I'm going to get him on this one.
I mean, bad enough I'm boiling in a bag.
Bye.
Now I gotta hear this.
Oh well.
I mean, the book came out four months ago.
Shouldn't you have another one by now or?
It's coming.
All right.
Well, actually there's like a point, one five coming.
And then another one coming.
Oh, that's true.
I'm not going to elaborate on that anymore.
That's true.
Yeah, I don't want to reveal that to everybody.
because what you're talking about has not been released.
Yes, I'll just let that sit.
Yeah.
Let people puzzle over it for generations.
What does that mean?
What do you see referring to with the point five?
Let's do some geometry on that.
A geometry?
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
So all right.
Well, it's the third half.
You know, I read in our group recently,
someone was really bugged by that.
They're like, why do they say third half?
It's like, well, training you to deal with a little bit of ambiguity is one of our side missions here in the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Yeah, if you can't roll with us on that, like, we got a lot of stuff in this show that you're not prepared.
I know one person was like, well, someone please explain this third half thing to me.
Look, it's a show and a half. What can I say?
Yeah, yeah, so all right well in the first half we talked about
appearing, right? Coming appearing, Parocia, Epiphania, whatever, Apocalypse. And then the
second half, if you're just joining us, we're talking about the idea that there is this
period between Christ's and Throne, and at the right hand of the Father, and then the
second appearing, the second appearing, that he's doing something in the midst of that
time. So yeah, so what does this have to do with the end?
end and right yeah so well you know if people went and read Psalms 1 10 and
Psalm 2 they know that Christ has been returned and filled the earth with
corpses right very Christ-like behavior because he's literally Christ yes but no
that's talking about the defeat of the spiritual enemies like we mentioned but
Yet there are other realities.
tied to this, right, to Christ glorious appearing.
And not just the other topics we've talked about
in other eschatology episodes.
And part of the key to understanding this is
understanding some things about the way
Christ's resurrection is described.
which of course precedes his ascension and enthronement.
And that centers around the language that's used concerning Christ of him being the first
fruits of the resurrection.
So for example, one of the identifiers of who Christ is in Revelation 1 verse 4, there's
a whole series of titles there.
The surrounding verses, but...
One of them is the first born from the dead.
The same language is used in Colossians 1 verse 18.
He is the head of the body of the church.
He is the beginning, the first born from the dead,
then in everything he might be preeminent.
That's first born, 1 Corinthians 15 verse 20,
1 Corinthians 15, the whole chapter is Saint Paul talking about.
Uh...
the resurrection of Christ and the resurrection in general. In verse 20 he calls Christ the first
fruits of them that slept. That's more King James for you. Yeah. I never get tired of that language.
It's so good. And it acts 26, verse 23, in St. Paul's sermon there, he refers to Christ as the
first to rise from the dead.
which, you know, someone might be thinking,
now wait a minute, wait a minute.
Okay, first to rise from the dead.
Didn't Lazarus rise from the dead?
Didn't Jesus raise a couple of other people?
Yeah, the son of the widow of Nain, yeah, Elias.
I mean, there's, you know, the unnamed guy
whose body got dropped on the bones of Elisha,
because, you know, Relics do that sometimes.
So, I mean, that's...
I think that when people think that, which, I mean,
there's a natural question to have, right?
I think that they believe, or they conceptualize that
rising from the dead means simply coming back to life.
Like resuscitation.
Recessitation, yeah, exactly.
They hit you with the paddles.
You start breathing again.
Right, right.
Which isn't actually how those paddles work,
but I digress.
I've never, they work in TV and movies.
I've never had them used on me, so I really don't know.
Yeah.
But yeah, I mean, it's-
I'm waiting.
Eventually, there'll be some trend where people just use them on each other at parties
or something.
We'll get there.
We got to tie pods.
We'll get there too.
De-fib parties.
This is the darkest timeline.
Yeah.
Right.
So this is where that first fruits language becomes important.
Because
When St. Paul is talking about the resurrection in 1 Corinthians 15, he's talking about something
different than just that kind of resuscitation, right?
Just that kind of biological life being restored as it is now, but you're still mortal, right?
So Lazarus died again eventually, as did all of those other folks that we mentioned.
And St. Paul uses specifically
the agricultural metaphors, right?
So a seed goes into the ground and it dies, right?
What it was dies, it breaks open, it breaks apart,
and then it becomes something else.
It grows into something else.
And that's his kind of length of describing
the resurrection at the end.
So there's this element of transformation, of growth
and transformation that requires the
old to die, to whether to be broken away. Right. And so then this is pointing to this language
itself points to the difference between Christ's resurrection and those other people being brought
back from the dead in that Christ is raised and his body is transformed. Yeah. And also, I mean,
This seems like an obvious point, but
All those other people died again,
whereas Christ will die no more.
Because, not because, like, surprise,
let's just keep waiting and see if he dies again.
It's that the way that his body functions,
his human body functions is now significantly different
after the resurrection.
Right.
And so the first fruits, right,
is the first of the crime.
to spring up, right?
And if you're familiar with the Torah,
there's an offering of first fruits.
You go and take those first fruits
and you offer them to God, you burn them up.
Right.
And this is, we have to, in order to understand ritual,
ritual like this, we have to understand
what is the state this induces in the participant.
Right, how does this affect?
What does it do and how does it affect how the participant
experiences the world?
Right, if I'm a subsistence farmer,
if the survival of my children depends on me
having a good crop this year, right?
Then when I get that first crop that springs up,
my natural and clinician is going to be, okay,
harvest this, keep it.
because a lot of things
things could happen between now and the rest of the harvest coming.
That could wipe out all or most of the rest of it.
But then at least I would have this.
At least I would have these first roots.
And God says, no, you take those and you give them to me.
You burn them up.
Which requires that person then, who is offering that to God as a thank-offering.
offering thanks for a harvest that hasn't come yet.
This requires the ultimate kind of trust within faithfulness that the rest is going to come.
And so St. Paul describing Christ as the first fruit is especially apt here.
His resurrection is not only sort of the place where we see what ours might look like
and so far as we can possibly understand it.
Bye.
But it is also the guarantee that causes us to then trust that the rest will happen in the future.
Also, this connection to first-roots, maybe the first inkling, some of our attentive listeners might have.
That this is actually a sneaky transfiguration episode.
It's going to get less sneaky as we go through the rest of the talk.
I tell you.
So when talking about the resurrection, right, because of course what happens at Christ's
second coming is the resurrection of the dead.
And in talking about that resurrection in 1 John 3 verse 2, St. John says, beloved, now
we are children of God, what we will be has not yet appeared.
But we know that when he appears, we'll be like him.
we will see him as he is.
So the appearing of Christ triggers this transformation of humanity.
Both the humans who are alive at that point and those who have died.
So Christ's appearance then triggers the St. Paul's harvest, right?
If that's the resurrection, the rest of the crop, right?
coming in.
But St. Paul and Romans, Romans 8 goes even farther than that than just talking about humanity.
Yeah, so you've got...
What Romans 8, starting verse 19, we're not going to read the whole chapter.
St. Paul says this, for the creation weights with
for the revealing of the sons of God.
For the creation was subjected to futility, not willingly,
but because of him who subjected it in hope,
that the creation itself will be set free
from its bondage to corruption,
and obtain the freedom of the glory of the children of God.
For we know that the whole creation
has been groaning together in the pains of childbirth
until now, and not only the creation,
but we ourselves, who have the first fruits of the Spirit,
grown inwardly as we wait eagerly for adoption as sons.
the redemption of our bodies, for in this hope we were saved.
Now hope that is seen is not hope for who hopes for what he sees.
But if we hope for what we do not see, we wait for it with patience.
Right.
So, Saint Paul has, you know, if we look at this as dominoes from St. John, right?
Christ appearing triggers this transformation of humanity,
this transformation of
humanity, the revelation, the appearing of the sons of God,
this triggers the transformation of creation as a whole.
Yeah, because of the whole creation,
is groaning for the revealing of the sons of God.
And this is, St. Paul is talking specifically
about the redemption of bodies, of the material world,
of the transformation and transfiguration of the world.
Sorry not, sorry not sticks.
Yeah, of the creation.
plug Robin Phillips book here. And this is in keeping with what St. Paul says for
example in Ephesians 1, 13 and 14 about the Holy Spirit being the down payment
on our salvation, the sort of deposit. So to go back to something we said all the
back in the first half right first Corinthians 15 St Paul
famously talks about us having a spiritual body in the resurrection.
And again, as we said, some people take that to mean, oh, spiritual, like
ephemeral. Yeah.
Woo, woo, like a start to get to where they become the evolved to be pure
energy. Yeah. Yeah.
Um, and no, again, this is capital S spirit.
Hmm. So this is a body that is permeated by the Holy Spirit.
Hmm.
And so what we're talking about is not just with humanity, but with the entirety of creation being suffused
with the light of the Holy Spirit, the presence of God.
And so we can say in a certain sense that the Holy Spirit is the atmosphere of the world to come.
Hmm.
And since now, we're probably pretty clearly outed ourselves to everyone,
as sneakily doing...
Transfiguration episode.
The Transfiguration is kind of a weird feast in
the sense that a lot of people don't know what to do with it
It's not sort of part of the right Christ is is born
The ministers in Galilee he goes to Jerusalem
He's crucified he rises he ascends into heaven he's seen it at the right hand of God right
Yeah, that's that sort of
storyline and the transformation is just sort of dropped in there.
Yeah, like wait, wait, he's doing what?
What?
Yeah.
Which, I mean, it's funny because I recently saw, and I mean a lot of people I think think
this way.
I actually recently saw, not that I've watched this show, although I actually had someone
contact me recently, say, you should watch this show, but that show the chosen, I haven't
seen it.
And frankly, I don't intend to see it.
but I saw this.
You know, I checked this to make this
sort of that this was real
because I actually posted about this
and a lot of people said that can't be real.
I was like, no, no, no, it's real.
The guy who directed that, he said something to the effect
of all these people, and they're asking me,
are we gonna have the transfiguration in our show?
And then he said, you know, what would that really add
to our story?
I was like, what?
Now, maybe he's messing with everybody, I don't know.
But I think that's an attitude that a lot of people have.
I was like, what is this here for?
Is it Jesus saying, oh, hey, by the way, I'm going.
God. You know, yeah, yeah. Or if you could even do that with it, right? So it's not,
in most church circles, right, it's not a heavy focus, right? The Orthodox Church is
where the 12 great feasts, right? But you go outside the Orthodox Church. It's not as
Well, emphasize, shall we say.
And in getting into why it's so important, right?
Obviously, one of the first places we go
is in the hemnography,
surrounding the feast.
And the hemnography surrounding the feast
makes it clear that this is happening
that Christ takes eight Peter's James and John
out of the mountain before the Passion.
Yeah.
Yep.
And so this has something to do.
with the fact that they're about to witness his suffering and crucifixion and death.
Yeah.
And so we can take it at kind of that surface level then and say, oh, well, okay,
they're about to witness that. So Christ is sort of revealing his divine identity to them
so that they won't fall into despair.
Yeah, which I mean is one of the texts that our hemnography takes.
Exit.
the only one. But it's at a very surface level. Yeah, yeah. It says, you know, uh,
revealed that, you know, you know, it's revealed I saw to the disciples. Uh, I think this is in the
Kentucky and so that when they would see the crucified, they would know that thy suffering was
voluntary. Like if, if that's who he really is, then yeah, I mean, he's, he's a, he's accepting
crucifixion. Right. Now if that's all that's going on there, it kind of didn't work.
Because we know that those three disciples did.
Yeah, right.
It's only John really, right?
It's the rings around.
Yeah, and even he, ultimately, right.
So I mean, he was with them hiding in the room, right?
He was there disbelieving the women.
Yeah, he was an out preaching.
Yeah.
So but there's sort of more to it than that, right?
This isn't just a question.
having Christ's identity confirmed. But they're seeing again with their physical eyes. Christ
it is uncreated glory which means they're getting a glimpse of the resurrection. Right? So, they are
be holding with their eyes the resurrected Christ before he died.
Yeah, think about that one for as I get everybody.
Yeah.
I'm in space aren't real guys.
But, you know, if you understand resurrection correctly, not just, you know, where he says, I am the resurrection, right?
Also a little mind bending, you know, if you think too much about it.
But if you understand the resurrection is not just about coming back to life,
but as about
the fullness of what a human is destined to be,
equal to the angels, all of that kind of stuff,
then that makes more sense.
It's about this elevation.
Right.
And so this is a glimpse of the resurrected Christ.
Christ's appearances after his resurrection,
his resurrection appearances are a glimpse
of the world to come.
There are series of glimpses and images we did in episode about them.
You can go back and listen to it.
There are series of glimpses of the world to come.
It's going to come after the general resurrection,
which is the general resurrection isn't just the resurrection of all the people.
It is all the people, but it's also the whole creation, the whole cosmos.
What does that look like?
On one hand, we don't know.
Right, I can't see.
and the details.
But what we have confirmed to us here in the New Testament
and in Christ is that the world to come is an actual world.
It's a material world, a material universe,
in which we'll have bodies.
Right?
And it is an actual life.
It's not just staring intently as a disembodied orb.
No pedaglory cloud.
Harps on class. Yeah. It's actual life in an actual world. And beyond that we can't understand, right?
Don't know what it's like to be a bat, right? Don't know what it's like to be a resurrected human in the world to come.
It's not just this world with all the bad stuff gone. Yeah. Right, this world with no pasta and bit of honey.
I think I trigger all those people again.
Yes.
someone's throwing their phone against the wall even as we speak.
Right, it's not just this world with the bad stuff taken out.
Right, it is a world that is transformed and suffused with the Holy Spirit.
Filled with people who are filled with and suffused with the Holy Spirit.
And I don't know what that's like.
Yeah.
We can't know what that's like until and unless we get there.
Yeah, I mean all we get is, like we see little vision.
We see little glimpses at sometimes, but that's not the same as being being there of doing it, you know
Yeah, yeah, and so we've said all this now about this being the whole cosmos being resurrected and all the people
being resurrected and this actual life in the actual world to come
But what about what if there's somebody
Who looks at that and says.
Nah.
Who doesn't wanna be a part of that?
Yeah.
That's what we're talking about next time.
That's, yeah.
That's our next episode.
Yeah.
Well, this turned out to be a relatively short one.
It's kind of, I'm a little shocked honestly.
Still over two hours.
Yeah, that's true, but you know,
I guess if the-
going to be any episode where no man knows the day nor the hour. This would be the one.
Yes.
When I get to go home and go to sleep.
So, you know, right, I'm not going to read from Lake Gray Planet Earth by Hal Lindsey
as tempted as I am to do that. But I didn't want to talk a little bit about the, you know,
We ended up with a transfiguration in a lot of this.
And I think that there's another angle
from which to understand the transfiguration
that makes a lot of this clear,
or maybe gives us just another way to contemplate
this amazing, amazing reality that we're talking about.
And that is, if we think about the Garden of Eden,
right, and we think about also the fact
that Moses and Elias are standing there
with the Lord on that mountain.
So, if you think about Eden, right?
And we've talked about this before in the show,
but I'll just to keep, you know,
maybe you guys didn't listen
to the spiritual geography episodes,
which I recommend you do.
Sacred geography, I should say.
You know, Eden is on a mountain,
which is not maybe super obvious from the Genesis text,
although there's talked about four rivers flowing out,
which means at least that it's on an elevated place,
because rivers flow out from elevated places.
That's how gravity works.
but then if you get to it.
I think is Ezekiel 28, Ezekiel 28 speaks about when the devil is thrown out of paradise.
It says he is on Eden and then he was thrown down from the mountain of God.
So it's very clear that Eden is a mountain in that text.
So Eden is a mountain and it's a garden on a mountain where God dwells with his people,
right?
It's the way that God created everything to be.
And then let's think about Moses and Elias for...
minute. So Moses who appears with the Lord on Mount Tabour at the
Transfiguration, he has spoken with God in the Old Testament in the Torah on
Mount Sinai, right? In the hymns for Transfiguration there's references to the
mountain covered with smoke. Well that's not Tabour. Tabour doesn't get covered
with smoke. That's Sinai where there was smoke and all these other signs that
they saw there. And the Lord showed...
Moses the vision of the creation and gives him the Torah and he brings it down to the people of Israel
and his face is shining. He is transfigured such that the people can't look at him and he has to be
veiled in order for them to be able to look at him. So that's Moses with God on the mountain
sharing this communion with him, right? And then also think about Elias. He's a Mount Horeb
And he also has a vision of...
God in the mountain.
It's a little bit different.
Moses speaks with the Lord face to face as a man speaks with his friend, but then also
has this vision where he can't look at him, he can't look at his face.
And then Alize's vision is more like that.
He experiences this mighty wind, there's earthquake and fire, and then this gentle breeze
or still small voice depending on which translation you're reading.
and he hears him there and he comes out and he has to wrap his face in his mouth.
mantle because he can't look at God and live. Right? So Elias also meeting with God on the mountain and having this
experience within this vision, this
communion.
So on
Tabor,
Christ is there and again, it's Moses and Elias and they're on a mountain together and Peter James and John are there as well.
One of the hymns, so if you come to Matins, which people come to Matins, you do not know what your
saying, please come to Mattins or Orthros, which if you're an anti-Okinia,
to Greek churches on Sunday morning before the divine liturgy, if you're a Russian
tradition church, it might be if they're doing it on Saturday night, paired with
Vespers as vigil, but come to Mattins. One of the hymns of Mattins says that,
and I'm paraphrasing a little bit here, but it says that on
In Tebur, Christ appears in glory with Moses and Elias to show...
that in the age to come that he will stand in the midst of the gods. That's what it says
in that hymn. And so if you look at the Transfiguration, that's what you see is going on, that
it is Christ ruling over the Divine Council. And there's a reason that we chose the icon
of the Transfiguration as being part of the logo of this podcast, because this is what's
going on.
in the feast, the transfiguration. And if you understand all these mountains in the right way,
and you understand what it means for human beings to be resurrected and to be transfigured and to
become truly like Christ, to be adopted sons of God, then you understand that as Father said,
that we're looking at the resurrection, we're looking at the kingdom. This is the kingdom of God.
And what do you know in the chapter right before it? Jesus says there's some standing here.
will not die before they've seen the kingdom of God coming in power. And the
offlact of Oak Ridge, and I'm sure probably other saints, I know that he said this
because I just read it this past week. He says that the reason that Jesus said
that in the chapter before is because of what he was about to do on Mount
Tabore, meaning that what we see on Tabore is the kingdom of God. That's what
that is. Right? So as we think about Christ's glorious
appearing, the transfiguration is not an event that happens in its deepest sense
before it. The transfiguration is actually the moment when we see it revealed to
us in a partial way. It's not in its total fulfillment as yet, but there is a very
real sense in which what is visible at the transfiguration? Jesus standing there
out table Moses and Elias there with him Peter James and John.
with them who, as some of the church fathers say, they themselves were
transfigured somewhat because that's what enabled them to see the
transfiguration that all of this together is what the second appearing of the
Lord is about. And it is what we're aiming towards as Christians. That's what
Christianity is for, is for that.
Right? And you know, this kind of
millenarian thing that a lot of Christians have,
including, I'm sorry to say some Orthodox Christians who
should know better. Like they have this sense of,
oh, it's the time of Antichrist. I mean, we talked about this in
our any Christ episode, but do you know the scripture people?
Like it's in, it's in John's epistles.
Antichrist have come and are, you know, like it's always the,
It's been the time of the eating crack.
because wow, this is the time when the Lord is ruling in the midst of his enemies.
So it is the time of the Etychrist and has been for all this time.
And the problem with thinking that you know that the end of the world is going to happen any second.
Now that is literally true. It could happen, right?
But if you orient yourself towards that, not in a way where you are oriented to really repent,
really repent. But instead you're oriented to try and make other people do
stuff, you know, whether it's condemning them or pushing them or whatever it might be,
trying to cause schisms, messing with personers in their churches. All stuff happening
right now. If you're doing that, then you're not doing it right. You know, if you are
oriented towards the second appearance of Christ such that it's like, oh, I need to repent.
I need to repent. Then you are doing it right. But the reason that we're repenting is
not just like, oh, wow, there's something big and bad happening. I don't want that to happen
to me. Although, okay, I mean, again, see our next episode. But really, it's wow, the
transfiguration, wow, the resurrection. I want to be part of that. And I can be part
of that. And the reason I can be part of that is because I'm saved by grace through faithfulness.
So be faithful.
Be more faithful.
Increase your faithfulness.
That's what the product...
So as Christ is ruling in the midst of his enemies,
as he's driving them out from every corner of the earth,
we participate in that by driving them out
from the corners of our own hearts.
Right? Not by treating other human beings
as though they are the enemy, they are not.
If they are acting like the enemy,
then that's because they're slaves.
They're slaves to the enemy.
And we want them to repent too.
We want them to be brothers and sisters too.
We want them to be with us too.
That's what it means to be Christian.
Right?
Do we love them?
It's a good question. So
Yeah, there's there's so much going on here and
in a real sense all those mountains Eden Sinai, Horeb, Tabore
We could also add in Herman and Zafon and some other stuff of when I get really deep and weird
But long time listeners of the podcast know what I'm talking about all of those mountains and these meetings with God these
Is it real?
these dwellings with God in a real sense are kind of all happening at the same time, the same place
because whatever is truly righteous enters into eternity and becomes in a way permanently present,
past, present, future, beyond time. It's awesome. It's awesome to think about. So, I mean, we should be
truly looking forward to the second and glorious appearing of the Lord. But
But on.
not in a way that's about fear and anger and, you know, hyperactivity and, you know,
hyperventilating and other hypers. That's not what's going on here. So it's time to repent.
It's time to repent. Father?
So dovetailing off that a little bit.
One of the major...
important things, I think that hopefully we got across tonight, is that this period
between Christ's ascension and his glorious appearing is not sort of him hitting pause
on accomplishing the Messiah's stuff. That Christ is that this agent which you and I
Bye.
We're born and will live out our lives is a part of what Jesus does as the Christ, as
the Messiah, ruling in the midst of his enemies.
He is active.
He is at work in the world continuously.
And that means it's also not a pause for us.
It's not a waiting room.
It's not about doing our best not to commit any sins to horrible before we check out.
It's not about, it's not even just about repenting of our sins in this world.
A lot of times we lose sight, even as Orthodox Christians,
the Orthodox Church.
There's a lot more emphasis placed on theosis, for example.
And anyone will tell you that, yes, we believe theosis is salvation.
Theosis is salvation.
But we still tend to fall into talking about our salvation in mostly negative terms.
I mean, there's a reason for that.
Like for me, most of what I'm at work on doing right now, the present moment, is repenting
of my m-
sense. Right? That's the major way in which for me the positive aspect of drawing closer to God
is happening is I'm still working my way out of the mud. Right? I'm not at the getting cleaner and
cleaner stage. I'm at the extricate yourself from the pit. But there is that other stage. There
is that positive? That...
positive element of our salvation.
And that is that contrary to what some of our non-Orthodox Christian friends
at least have in their theology books, glorification, as it's called, is not just
something that happens after we die.
It's not just something that happens after Christ returns.
but it's so...
something that is beginning now, something that is active in the world now. The Holy Spirit
is active in the world now. And while he has not yet fully suffused the whole creation
and my whole being is a person, he is still here and he is still active. And so this life
is not just a question of repentance.
or of enduring suffering and hardship.
Both of those are realities for us.
But it's also a life in a world where moments, where days, where friendships,
where marriages, where all kinds of spiritual relationships
can be suffused with the light and the love and the peace
that the Holy Spirit brings.
where these glimpses of the resurrection are possible and when they happen they are real.
Just like St. Peter got turned down when he wanted to build the booths on the Mount of Transfiguration
and stay there forever, those moments don't last for us forever.
And you can go and read the lives of St. Sarah from Sarah of St.
the New Theologian saints who received the vision of Christ and uncreated glory, talking
about the fact that even for them is a great saint. Far more holy and closer to God than
I will ever be. That vision did not last their entire life. It was a fleeting experience,
a powerful experience, but a fleeting one.
And these other realities of...
of repentance and of suffering and of joy in this world,
all returned afterwards.
So I don't want to leave off this episode,
especially given the topic of next episode,
just gonna be kind of a downer,
without that positive aspect.
That the Holy Spirit is the deposit
and the down payment of that world to come,
that he is here now.
that we do receive these glimpses in these moments,
and that we can be about trying to infuse through love,
through joy, through making peace.
We can go out and actively infuse moments of our life
and parts of our life and areas of our life
with that grace of the Holy Spirit,
even if it is fleeting.
But those glimpses we get of glory
are what then empowers us
to deal with the other harder.
things that we have to do and we have to endure in this life.
Amen. Amen.
Well, even though it's been two hours and sixteen minutes,
that's our show for tonight.
Thank you very much everyone for listening.
If you didn't happen to call us and get through live,
we'd like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritsanEatinfeet.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page.
You can send me reviews of all the works of how Lindsay
and leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash Lord of Spades.
I mainly want to review Barney Miller.
Join us for our live broadcast of the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m.
Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
And if you are on Facebook, you can follow our page and join our discussion group, leave
reviews and ratings everywhere and memes naturally.
But most importantly, share this show with a friend when you know who's going to love it.
And finally, be sure to go to ancientfaith.com, stroke support and help make sure we
and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air
and Father Andrew stays in the air
to see travels from country to country.
Thank you, good night and may God bless you and keep you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father
Andrew Stephen Damick.
Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses
11-12.